Guide to the Brown Brothers Harriman Records 1696-1973, 1995 (bulk, 1820-1968) MS 78
New-York Historical Society
- Series VIII. Visual Material and Audio Tapes (1830s-1995), 4 Linear feet 10 document boxes, XX oversize folders
  - Subseries A. Assorted Visual Material (1832-1968, 1995)
    The glass plate negatives of John Crosby Brown's New Jersey home, Brighthurst, were donated to the Historical Files in 1966 by his grandson John Crosby Brown Moore.
    The black and white photographs by Guy Gillette and Matar Studios were commissioned for use in the second edition of the brochure "Personality of a Bank", issued in 1967. The firm's first promotional publication, it was originally issued in 1959. Further information about the publication, including additional prints, is included in the "1959" files in Subseries I.A. Chronological Files.
    Some images from the 1968 sesquicentennial celebrations (provided by the Union Pacific Railroad) in Seattle and Sun Valley were reproduced in personalized leather-bound scrapbooks presented to each guest. The book presented to Juan Trippe, who as president of Pan American World Airways was instrumental in inspiring Boeing to create the 747 jetliner, is item 109 in the Print Room's album collection at New-York Historical Society.
    Some snapshots from the Sun Valley events were contributed to the Historical Files by Alice B. Brown, wife of partner Moreau Delano Brown; others were taken by Malcolm Freudy of Freudy Photos, New York City.
    The 1995 materials consist of two groups (marked A and B) of images originally from the Historical Files and from the Walker Evans portfolio (see Subseries VIII.B.), which were rehoused separately from the other visual materials in 1995. No explanation for this is provided in the Collection. Image A12 is now included in the oversize materials.
    The vast preponderance of visual materials in the Collection can be found in Subseries I.A. and Subseries I.B., arranged either chronologically or by subject, respectively.
    As part of the firm's 150th anniversary celebrations in September, 1968, it hosted a multiday excursion to Sun Valley, Idaho (developed as a ski resort in the 1930s by the Harriman interests), for clients and guests who included American industrialists and overseas bankers, but no American commercial bankers. It began in Seattle, Washington, with dinner one evening at the Space Needle and the next at the home of Boeing's president William Allen, after guests had had a tour of the Boeing facility where the first 747 jetliner was being constructed. From Seattle, guests boarded two Union Pacific trains for the trip overland to Shoshone, Idaho, and traveled thence by bus to Sun Valley for two days of seminars, social events, and leisure activities.
    A celebration for staff, families, and guests was held in New York on October 9, 1968. It began with an Open House at the firm's headquarters at 59 Wall Street and continued at a re-creation of the 1818 New York waterfront on pier 13 at the foot of Wall Street. It featured food, drinks, and entertainment of the period, with catering by Restaurant Associates. Among the guests was New York Mayor John V. Lindsay.
    The five glass plate negatives showing rooms at John Crosby Brown's New Jersey home, Brighthurst; the two framed portraits of Montagu Norman; and the view of James Brown's house at 9th Street and University Place were removed from Subseries I.C.vi. Partners. They are housed separately from the other materials in this subseries because of their size and fragility.
    The stereograph images were found loose in John Crosby Brown's 1859-1860 scrapbook of pressed plants and flowers (Subseries V.B. Partners. John Crosby Brown, volume 36).
    The prints, contacts, and negatives by photographer Guy Gillette and by Matar Studios were originally housed with materials included in Subseries VIII.B. Walker Evans Portfolio, and have been moved here for consistency.
    - Notice of U.S. Mail steamers, New York to Liverpool, including Arctic, 1855 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 4)
    - Stereograph images from John Crosby Brown scrapbook, 1859-1860 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 5)
    - Bank draft; explanatory note, 1866 February 28, 1929 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 6)
    - Sanitary Commission War Claim Association document, naming partner Howard Potter, Commissioner, 1866 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence accompanying pictures for framing and reproduction, 1921, 1923 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 8)
    - Notes accompanying Howard Maeder donation of Romer document, circa 1927 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 9)
    - Guy Gillette photos: 59 Wall Street exteriors (color transparencies, 1959, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 10)
    - Notes, wording, estimate for Alexander Brown plaque, 1964 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 11)
    - Guy Gillette photos: Investment Committee - black and white prints (1/5), 1965 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 12)
    - Guy Gillette photos: Credit conferences - black and white prints and contacts (2/5), 1965-1967 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 13)
    - Guy Gillette photos: Policy Review Committee - black and white prints (3/5), 1965 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 14)
    - Guy Gillette photos: Account and Prospect Review Committee - black and white prints (4/5), 1966 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 15)
    - Guy Gillette photos: partners in the conference/map room - black and white prints (5/5), 1965 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 16)
    - Guy Gillette photo: New York's financial center - color negative, 1965 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 17)
    - Guy Gillette photos: medallion, 59 Wall Street - black and white prints, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 18)
    - Guy Gillette photos: rotunda and Alexander Brown statue, 59 Wall Street - black and white prints, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 19)
    - Guy Gillette photos: rotunda and Alexander Brown statue, 59 Wall Street - 5 x 7 black and white prints, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 20)
    - Matar Studio photos: rotunda and Alexander Brown statue, 59 Wall Street - 8 x 10 black and white prints, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 118, Folder 21)
    - James Brown residence: 9th Street and University Place - glass plate negative, 1850s (Box 119, Folder 1)
    - Brighthurst interior - glass plate negative, circa 1880 (Box 119, Folder 2)
    - Brighthurst interior - glass plate negative, circa 1880 (Box 119, Folder 3)
    - Brighthurst interior - glass plate negative, circa 1880 (Box 119, Folder 4)
    - Brighthurst interior - glass plate negative, circa 1880 (Box 119, Folder 5)
    - Brighthurst interior - glass plate negative, circa 1880 (Box 119, Folder 6)
    - Montagu Norman portrait, 1908 (Box 119, Folder 7)
    - Montagu Norman portrait, 1908 (Box 119, Folder 8)
    - Guy Gillette photos: 59 Wall Street exterior - black and white prints and color print, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 1)
    - Guy Gillette photos: 59 Wall Street exterior - black and white transparencies, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 2)
    - Guy Gillette photos: 59 Wall Street exterior - color transparencies, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 3)
    - Matar Studio photos: 59 Wall Street exteriors - color negatives and transparencies, 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 4)
    - Guy Gillette photos: interior and exterior shots - edited contact sheets, 1967 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 5)
    - Guy Gillette photos: exterior 59 Wall Street - color transparencies, circa 1967 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 6)
    - Matar Studio: 59 Wall Street corner entrance - color transparency and negative (Offsite-box 120, Folder 7)
    - 150th anniversary: Sun Valley, ID - Alice B. Brown color snapshots, 1968 September (Offsite-box 120, Folder 8)
    - 150th anniversary: Union Pacific train interiors and exteriors; Seattle Space Needle - black and white prints, color negative, 1968 September (Offsite-box 120, Folder 9)
    - 150th anniversary: Seattle, Sun Valley - color snapshots by Freudy Photos, 1968 September (Offsite-box 120, Folder 10)
    - 150th anniversary: Union Pacific train, interiors and exterior - black and white prints, 1968 September (Offsite-box 120, Folder 11)
    - 150th anniversary: alienated envelope ("Mr. and Mrs. W.G. Pullen"), 1968 September (Offsite-box 120, Folder 12)
    - 150th anniversary: Seattle, Union Pacific trains, correspondence, 1968 September, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 13)
    - 150th anniversary: staff party, Wall Street pier - color slides; stamped Life Magazine, 1968 October 9 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 14)
    - 150th anniversary: staff party, Wall Street pier - color prints; stamped Time magazine, 1968 October 9 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 15)
    - Rehoused images from Historical Files: Series A - black and white prints, 1995 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 16)
    - Rehoused images from Historical Files and Walker Evans portfolio: Series B - black and white prints, mounted print, 1995 (Offsite-box 120, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified wood backing, Undated (Offsite-box 120, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified retouched photo: stairs and arbor, Undated (Offsite-box 120, Folder 19)
    - Framing store labels, Undated (Offsite-box 120, Folder 20)
    - 100th anniversary club, Philadelphia - black and white print, circa 1918 (Offsite-box OS 11, Folder 6)
    - John A. Brown, circa 1830 (Offsite-box OS 12, Folder 4)
    - Alexander Brown, 1832 (Offsite-box OS 12, Folder 5)
    - William Brown, 1840s (Offsite-box OS 12, Folder 6)
    - James Brown, based on Brady "Imperial" photo, circa 1857 (Offsite-box OS 12, Folder 7)
    - William Brown, 1858 (Offsite-box OS 12, Folder 8)
    - Howard Potter, 1880s (Offsite-box OS 12, Folder 9)
    - Eugene Delano, circa 1915 (Offsite-box OS 12, Folder 10)
    - Pastel sketch for Alexander Brown plaque, 1964 (Offsite-box OS 12, Folder 11)
    - "The Exchange, New York" - engraving, 1854 (Offsite-box OS 13, Folder 4)
    - Liverpool: Shipley offices - photoreproduction, circa 1908 (Offsite-box OS 13, Folder 5)
    - Certificate to James Brown from Ferdinand of Rumania, 1927 (Offsite-box OS 13, Folder 6)
    - Jay Robinson sketches of Liverpool buildings, 1965 (Offsite-box OS 13, Folder 7)
    - 63 Wall Street: entrance and building, 1968 (Offsite-box OS 13, Folder 8)
    - Photostat reproductions of documents, 1825, 1915, 1917 (Offsite-box OS 14, Folder 1)
    - Rehoused image: Walker Evans portfolio, 1995 (Offsite-box OS 14, Folder 2)
    - Photomontage rendering, 59-63 Wall Street building: Delano & Aldrich Architects, circa 1929 (Offsite-box BBH-58, Box OS 15)
    - Sun Valley 150th anniversary events: original watercolor cartoon by Roy Doty, 1968 (Offsite-box BBH-58, Box OS 15)
    - Group portrait, U.S./ U.K. Trade Conference (photoreproduction) [signed by W. Averell Harriman], 1941 (Drawer OS D1900)
    - Exterior photographs, Brown Brothers Harriman building, Wall Street, 1960s (Drawer OS D1900)
  - Subseries B. Walker Evans Portfolio (1964-1967, 1975)
    The subseries includes black and white prints, negatives, contact sheets, captions, correspondence, and ephemera related to Walker Evans's portfolio of photographs commissioned for publication as the conclusion of Partners in Banking.
    Partners in Banking was designed as an image-heavy history of the firm. However, because much of the company's evolution after 1945 did not provide extensive graphic material, Kouwenhoven decided to end the book with a commissioned photographic portfolio depicting the contemporary organization, its partners, and locations.
    For this he chose photographer Walker Evans, who was ending his career as Special Photographic Editor at Fortune Magazine. During his tenure there from 1945 to 1964, Evans had completed numerous self-assigned photographic studies of the contemporary business environment, its practitioners and tools. He brought to these the same eye for detail and sociological import that had informed his best-known and most provocative images: those documenting rural poverty for the Resettlement (later, Farm Security) Administration during the Depression, and his photographs of Greensboro, Alabama, farming families originally published, with James Agee, as Let Us Now Praise Famous Men in 1941.
    The Brown Brothers Harriman portfolio may be the last that Evans made as a corporate documenter, and only 56 of the close to 300 images he made for the project were published in Partners in Banking. In 1965 he was named Professor of Photography on the Faculty for Graphic Design at the Yale School of Art and Architecture. Before his death in 1975, Evans experimented with the new instant Polaroid SX-70 camera and lectured and published on his collections of vernacular images, including an extensive postcard collection.
    The subseries is organized in three sections:
    Subseries VIII.B.i. Correspondence and notes
    Subseries VIII.B.ii. Prints and captions
    Subseries VIII.B.iii. Contact sheets and negatives
    Related Archival Materials in Other Repositories
    The Metropolitan Museum of Art holds the Walker Evans Archive, which includes negatives and contacts of some of these images, and a small amount of related correspondence. It is the copyright owner of all images produced by Evans, including those in the Brown Brothers Harriman Collection.
    - Subseries B.i. Correspondence and notes (1964-1966, 1975), 0.43 Linear feet 1 document box
      The subseries includes Kouwenhoven's initial proposal of the project to Evans, provides information about Evans' shooting schedule at the various Brown Brothers Harriman offices and partners' homes, and documents his expenses for travel, film, and other equipment necessary for the project.
      The materials in the subseries originated in three envelopes housed in various places with the photographic materials. They are arranged in chronological order.
      - Kouwenhoven proposal letter to Walker Evans; other correspondence; copy of Walker Evans notebook, 1964 April 20, September 8; 1965 (Offsite-box 121, Folder 1)
      - "Photo project: letter, note and record file, including expenses": notes and correspondence, including Evans's shooting schedule (1/3), 1964-1965 (Offsite-box 121, Folder 2)
      - "Photo project: letter, note and record file, including expenses": black and white work prints of interior renovation; photocopy (2/3), 1964 July (Offsite-box 121, Folder 3)
      - "Photo project: letter, note and record file, including expenses": arrangements, receipts for lodging, travel, processing (3/3), 1965 April - July (Offsite-box 121, Folder 4)
      - "Walker Evans": New York Times obituary, July 1964 shooting schedule, notes on locations, 1964, 1975 (Offsite-box 121, Folder 5)
      - "Sarah B. Brown's notes for captions of Evans pics used in book" [includes 2-1/4 inch prints and negatives] (Offsite-box 121, Folder 6)
      - Receipts and expenses, 1966 November (Offsite-box 121, Folder 7)
      - Unused photo processing mailer, Modernage Photographic Services, New York City, 1960s (Offsite-box 121, Folder 8)
    - Subseries B.ii. Prints and captions (1964-1967), 2.5 Linear feet 6 document boxes
      The mounted prints were prepared for Kouwenhoven as aids to editing Evans's portfolio for publication in Partners in Banking. A sample card provided by Evans, with a handwritten and signed explanation, appears to be the prototype.
      Each mount is stamped with the Historical Files' stamp and dated. Many are accompanied by separate captions in Sarah B. Brown's hand (some edited in another hand); photocopies of her originals; and/or typed captions on adhesive-backed paper, some adhered to the mount and some loose. Some of the Philadelphia office photographs are captioned on the back in pencil, in Evans's hand. Images used in the book ("P.I.B") are marked on the back with their respective page numbers.
      His biographer, Jeff Rosenheim, has described Evans's business-environment photographs as documenting "the office as cultural artifact." These images of wealthy and powerful men, in their work and home environments and with the tools and possessions that define them, can easily be compared with Evans's images of farmers and migrant workers who are likewise defined by their bereft environment and paltry possessions.
      The materials were originally stored in three large record center cartons. They have been rehoused in acid-free folders in archival document boxes. The accompanying captions, originally paper-clipped to the mounted prints, have been preservation photocopied and precede the prints that they describe. The prints are ordered as they were in the original boxes, using the descriptions on the dividers that identified groups of images. There is significant repetition of images in some of the groups. The numbering of these boxes is out of order because of their different sizes.
      - Exterior Philadelphia office; New York offices of partners Lovett, Ireland, Gerry and Shipley, Kingsbury, 1965 March 31; 1966 October 6, November 17 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 1)
      - Partners Room and desks, New York City; Philadelphia office interior, 1965 March 31; 1966 November 17 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 2)
      - Partners and office, New York City: E.R. Harriman, West, Woolley, Bush, Lovett, 1964 July 24; 1966 November 17 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 3)
      - Partners Harriman, Bush, Woolley, Lovett: Walker Evans's sample card layout, annotated and signed, 1964 July 28 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 4)
      - Partners Kingsbury, Woolley, Lovett, Bush, Harriman, 1964 July 24, 28; 1967 March 2 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 5)
      - Partners Roosa, Kingsbury, Lovett, Hord; Lovett office, 1966 October 6; 1967 April 27, May 4 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 6)
      - "St. Louis and Chicago partners" (photographed in New York; only Hord pictured), 1967 April 27 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 7)
      - Partner McCance and wife at Mt. Kisco, New York, home, 1967 May 20 (Offsite-box 122, Folder 8)
      - Partner McCance at Mt. Kisco, New York home; with John A. Kouwenhoven, 1967 May 20 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 1)
      - Woolley, Harriman, Kouwenhoven at Harriman estate "Arden", 1967 May 19 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 2)
      - 59 Wall Street exteriors, 1964 July 7; 1967 February 1 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 3)
      - Unidentified man at typewriter [unlabeled; may not be Brown Brothers Harriman], 1960s (Offsite-box 123, Folder 4)
      - Delmonico's restaurant; exterior 61-63 Wall Street, 1964 July 7; 1967 February 1 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 5)
      - Personnel Department, New York City, 1967 February 17 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 6)
      - Harriman estate "Arden": exteriors and car, 1967 May 19 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 7)
      - Woolley, Harriman, Kouwenhoven at Harriman estate "Arden", 1967 May 19 (Offsite-box 123, Folder 8)
      - Partner John Madden and family at home, 218 Columbia Heights, Brooklyn, New York, 1967 February 25 (Offsite-box 124, Folder 1)
      - Banking platform, 59 Wall Street, 1966 October 13, November 17 (Offsite-box 124, Folder 2)
      - Banking platform, 59 Wall Street, 1966 October 13; 1967 March 1 (Offsite-box 124, Folder 3)
      - Banking platform, 59 Wall Street, 1966 October, November; 1967 February 23 (Offsite-box 124, Folder 4)
      - Partners McCance and Currier in Hanson office, New York City, 1966 December 1 (Offsite-box 124, Folder 5)
      - Partners McCance and Currier in Hanson office, New York City, 1966 December 1 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 1)
      - Bookkeeping department, 59 Wall Street, 1966 November 2 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 2)
      - Partners' dining rooms; luncheon, 1967 February 17 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 3)
      - Kitchen and staff, 1965 April 27 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 4)
      - Elevator and operator; Account Records department, 1965 March 26 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 5)
      - Construction on 2nd and 3rd floors, 59 Wall Street, 1964 July 30 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 6)
      - Employee cafeteria; records room; mail room, 1965 March 26; 1966 October 28, 1967 February 23 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 7)
      - John A. Kouwenhoven in Historical Files office, 1964 June 18 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 8)
      - Credit, Tax, Foreign Investment departments, 1965 March 26; 1966 November 2; 1967 March 2 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 9)
      - Foreign Investment, Investment, Investment Adivsory departments, 1966 November 2; 1967 March 2 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 10)
      - Bond, Foreign Exchange, Institutional departments, 1966 November 2; 1967 March 3 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 11)
      - Tax, Domestic Banking departments, 1966 November 2; 1967 March 2 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 1)
      - Research Department, 1967 February 23 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 2)
      - [Research Department], 1967 February 23 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 3)
      - Partner Moreau Brown in Philadelphia office, 1965 March 30 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 4)
      - Boston office: Driver and Rattray, 1965 July 13 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 5)
      - Boston office: partners Driver and Curtis; manager Hancort, 1965 July 13 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 6)
      - Philadelphia office; partner Moreau Brown at home; Irwin-Harrisons-Whitney tea company, 1965 March 31 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 7)
      - Philadelphia office; partner Moreau Brown, 1965 March 31 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 8)
      - Philadelphia office; partner Moreau Brown at home, 1965 March 30 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 9)
      - Irwin-Harrisons-Whitney tea company, Philadelphia, 1965 March 31 (Offsite-box 127, Folder 1)
      - Boston office: partners Curtis and Driver, 1965 July 13 (Offsite-box 127, Folder 2)
      - Boston partner Driver's home: Needham, Massachusetts, 1965 July 13 (Offsite-box 127, Folder 3)
      - Unmounted prints, captions, 1960s (Offsite-box 127, Folder 4)
      - Sample mounting boards for prints, 1960s (Offsite-box 127, Folder 5)
      - Separated captions, 1960s (Offsite-box 127, Folder 6)
    - Subseries B.iii. Contact sheets and negatives (1964-1967), 0.2 Linear feet 1/2 document box
      The subseries includes both 35 mm and 2.25 inch negatives and contact sheets for many of the images that Evans chose to print and that are included in Subseries VIII.B.ii. Prints and Captions. The china marker edits on the contact sheets show Evans's choices among the various shots he took at individual locations, and of people and groups. The notation "C" on the original glassine housing for the 35 mm negative strips would appear to document the Contax camera Evans used for this format, and the "R" on the 2.25 inch housing the Rolleiflex camera that he used for the latter.
      In one of the images of partner Thomas McCance's home that Evans chose not to print, the photographer's shadow is visible on the grass, bent as he would be over a view camera that he holds in front of him.
      The materials were originally grouped in manila envelopes and labeled by subject. Those groupings have been retained here and the materials are ordered as they originally were in the record center cartons. Most of the envelopes were not dated; dates have been added based on those provided on the mounted prints of the same images.
      A large group of manila envelopes was empty; these have been preservation photocopied and the originals disposed of.
      - Boston office and W.R. Driver's home, [1965 July 13] (Offsite-box 121, Folder 9)
      - New York office: bank floor corridor looking north; walls of E.R. Harriman private office; Woolley, [1964 July] (Offsite-box 121, Folder 10)
      - John A. Kouwenhoven and Sarah B. Brown in Historical Files office, Conference Room B, 4th floor; 59 Wall Street corner entrance; lobby stairs, [1964 June, July] (Offsite-box 121, Folder 11)
      - Senior partners Harriman, Lovett, Bush, Woolley in "new room", 59 Wall Street, 1964 July 28 (Offsite-box 121, Folder 12)
      - Platform from mezzanine; mezzanine; Account Records department; mail room, [1965 March 26] (Offsite-box 121, Folder 13)